{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One side in this battle halted fire due to a miscommunication about the remaining ammunition; to maintain morale, that side informed its men that the pause was to have breakfast. The direction “you may fire when you are ready, Gridley” was given to begin this battle. In this battle, George Dewey’s U.S. fleet lost one sailor to heatstroke and sunk 8 Spanish ships. For ten points, name this May 1, 1898 battle of the Spanish-American War, fought in the harbor of the Philippine capital city.",
      "answer": "Battle of Manila Bay do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "An army from this region intercepted King Josiah at Megiddo and killed him. Near the end of his life, the prophet Jeremiah was forced to move to this region against his will. A family fled to this region to escape King Herod’s decree to kill all boys two years or younger. The firstborn of every household in this region was slaughtered before its leader allowed the Israelites to leave. For ten points, name this region that, in numerous Biblical stories, was ruled by pharaohs.",
      "answer": "Egypt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The two Pelham brothers successively held this post; the elder was forced from office after the loss of Minorca. This position’s foundation came from Standing Order 66, which limits the proposal of expenditure bills. As a result of that order, the first holder of this position was also First Lord of the Treasury and came to power after the burst of the South Sea Bubble; that man was Robert Walpole. For ten points, name this political position whose holder lives in 10 Downing Street and is currently the head of Queen Elizabeth’s Cabinet.",
      "answer": [
        "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom or PM of UK",
        "Great Britain and/or England in place of UK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man sacked the castle of Jacob’s Ford after a bribe of 100,000 gold pieces to stop the castle’s construction was turned down. Though this man was defeated at the Battle of Montgisard, he later formed a truce with Baldwin IV. One campaign against this man was called after his victory at Hattin, though he ended that conflict by granting Christians safe pilgrimage to Jerusalem. For ten points, name this Kurdish founder of the Ayyubid dynasty, an enemy of Richard I in the Third Crusade.",
      "answer": "Saladin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This team lost a group of promising young players in the 1958 Munich air disaster, though a survivor of that crash, Bobby Charlton, held the goalscoring record for this club until 2017. A manager who gave locker room tirades known as “hairdryer treatments” won 13 Premier League titles with this club, which is currently managed by the Portuguese former manager of Chelsea, Jos´e Mourinho. Sir Alex Ferguson once coached, for ten points, what English soccer team led by Zlatan Ibrahimovic and Wayne Rooney?",
      "answer": "Manchester United F.C."
    },
    {
      "question": "Contemporary historian James Ronda has written several books about this event, one of which claims that a comparable event was led by James Mackay and John Thomas Evans. During this event, Fort Clatsop was constructed along the Columbia River. Participants in this event included a slave named York, Toussaint [too-sahn] Charbonneau, and Charbonneau’s Shoshone wife, Sacagawea. For ten points, name this voyage that explored the Missouri River, including much of the Louisiana Purchase.",
      "answer": [
        "Lewis and Clark Expedition",
        "Corps of Discovery"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In ancient times, this currency was worth 6 obols. In 1828, the phoenix replaced the Ottoman kurus, then itself was replaced four years later by the “phoenix,” adorned with King Otto’s face; both this currency and the phoenix were equivalent to 100 lepta. In 1973, this currency replaced the image of the deposed King Constantine with more phoenix imagery and the phrase “Hellenic Republic.” For ten points, name this currency used by both the ancient and modern, pre-Euro Greeks.",
      "answer": "drachma"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man testified on behalf of Robel Phillipos after the Boston Marathon bombing. In 1988, this man fired Donna Brazile for claiming his opponent was cheating with Jennifer Fitzgerald. During a presidential campaign, this man was attacked for supporting prisoner’s weekend furlough passes in the Willie Horton ad and for opposing “virtually every defense system” in the Tank ad. For ten points, name this former Massachusetts governor who lost to George H.W. Bush in 1988.",
      "answer": "Michael Dukakis"
    },
    {
      "question": "An issue of 291 magazine was entirely devoted to this work, possible because the magazine was founded by its artist. A man in a prayer shawl and several women in headscarves stand in the bottom third of this work, whose left side is dominated by a large rising mast and a white drawbridge. This modernist work was taken on the Kaiser Wilhelm II as it traveled from, not to, New York City, as is commonly assumed. For ten points, name this 1907 photograph of lower class passengers, taken by Alfred Stieglitz.",
      "answer": "The Steerage"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one work, Thomas Carlyle cites how this statement’s speaker could be met with “silence and abashed looks” after saying it. This statement’s speaker apparently contradicted this statement on his deathbed, noting that while he is “going away,” a certain entity “will always remain.” This statement was probably a fabrication by opponents of its speaker. For ten points, name this statement that may or may not have been said by Louis XIV in a demonstration of his absolutist power.",
      "answer": [
        "I am the state or L’´etat, c’est moi",
        "close translations along the lines of I myself am the nation"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This only piece of music this composer wrote for harp was a concerto featuring it with flute. This compoeser’s twenty-fifth piano concerto is nicknamed “Coronation” for its use during the ascension of Leopold II to Holy Roman Emperor. An opera by this composer, whose aria “Der Holle Rache” is known for its coloratura high Fs, had a libretto by Emmanuel Schikaneder that was probably inspired by Freemasonry. The Queen of the Night is found in, for ten points, what composer’s The Magic Flute?",
        "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other musician, who served as Austrian imperial Kapellmeister from 1788 to 1824, supposedly feuded with Mozart in a legend dramatized by Peter Shaffer’s play Amadeus.",
        "answer": "Antonio Salieri"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state’s capital was chosen to be at the site of LeFleur’s Bluff, overlooking the Pearl River. An alluvial plain in this state, home to the towns of Clarksdale and Greenville, is bounded on the east by the Yazoo River and is known for a distinctive variety of blues. Another city here was captured after a 47-day siege by Ulysses S. Grant in 1863. For ten points, a namesake Delta and the city of Vicksburg are located in what Southern state whose capital is Jackson?",
        "answer": "Mississippi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This city, the first capital of Mississippi, was the southern end of a trail used by both Native Americans and early European settlers known as its namesake “trace.”",
        "answer": "Natchez"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A tribe of these people called the Senones marched on Rome, demanding that Quintus Fabius be handed over; when he wasn’t, these people won the Battle of the Allia, then cheated the losers with weighted scales for measuring tribute. A chieftain of the Arverni tribe of these people led a massive rebellion of these people until his defeat at the Siege of Alesia. For ten points, name these people, the barbarian inhabitants of modern-day France during Roman times.",
        "answer": "Gauls"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This aforementioned Arverni chief won the Battle of Gergovia against Julius Caesar, but was paraded through Rome and executed by Caesar after he lost at Alesia.",
        "answer": "Vercingetorix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One ruler of this empire met his end after falling down a library staircase while attempting to heed a muezzin’s call to prayer. The Nine Jewels, including Birbal, were advisors to this empire, where the Din-i-ilahi religion was established in an attempt to merge Hinduism and Islam. This empire was established following Ibrahim Lodi’s defeat at Panipat in 1526. For ten points, name this Indian empire ruled by Humayun and Akbar.",
        "answer": "Mughal Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Humayun, the aforementioned ruler who fell down a staircase, was the son of this Mughal founder.",
        "answer": "Zahir-ud-din Muhammad Babur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side in this election year used the song “Hunters of Kentucky” to rally support. After suffering a stroke, William Crawford lost support and finished third in this election year. Thanks to the Twelfth Amendment, this election hung on a House of Representatives vote that the loser decried as a “corrupt bargain” struck by Henry Clay. For ten points, name this election year in which John Quincy Adams defeated Andrew Jackson.",
        "answer": "Presidential Election of 1824"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Crawford finished third in 1824, but he wasn’t a third party candidate; all four candidates that received Electoral College votes were members of this party, which essentially split apart when they failed to nominate a single candidate in 1824. ANSWER:Democratic-RepublicanParty(donotacceptorpromptonDemocraticorRepublicanalone) (6) David Markson’s best known work is titled for this philosopher’s “Mistress.” Bertrand Russell’s “The Philosophy of Logical Atomism” was based on one of this man’s works. This philosopher once threatened Karl Popper with a hot poker because Popper claimed the existence of moral rules. “The world is everything that is the case” opens a work by this man that he himself later critiqued in his posthumously published Philosophical Investigations. For ten points, name this Austrian philosopher who argued that all philosophical problems were mere “language-games” and wrote Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus.",
        "answer": "Ludwig Wittgenstein BONUS: Wittgenstein’s Tractatus was adored, albeit often misunderstood according to Wittgenstein himself, by members of this philosophical group. It essentially fell apart after the 1936 murder of Moritz Schlick, although many of its members had earlier fled from the Nazis. ANSWER: Vienna Circle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "On a 24-day tour of South America, this man noted that Alberto Santos-Dumont, rather than the Wright Brothers, deserved the title “Father of Aviation.” With David Scott, this man was a member of the second flight of Americans in space, Gemini 8. This man commanded a mission in which the Command Module Columbia was piloted by Michael Collins as he and Buzz Aldrin rode in the Eagle. For ten points, name this commander of Apollo 11.",
        "answer": "Neil Alden Armstrong"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This three-stage rocket brought Neil Armstrong and the other Apollo astronauts into low Earth orbit.",
        "answer": "Saturn V"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this man’s reign, his forces broke a blockade of the Hanko Peninsula in the Battle of Gangut, his country’s first naval victory. A major victory during his reign was the capture of Azov. He reorganized his government with the Table of Ranks and defeated a revolt by the streltsy. He studied shipbuilding in the Netherlands as part of his Great Tour to learn more about Western Europe. For ten points, name this “Great” modernizing tsar of Russia.",
        "answer": "Peter I or Peter the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of his westernization efforts, Peter imposed a tax on these people, empowering his police to shave their beards on the spot if they hadn’t paid for the right to wear them.",
        "answer": "boyars"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Ben Franklin",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Children’s toy he wanted to fly in a thunderstorm as a science experiment.",
          "answer": "kite with a key, attached to the end of the string, in a jar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern Ivy League school that Franklin founded as The Academy and College of Philadelphia.",
          "answer": "University of Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Annual publication by Franklin that included weather forecasts and his essay “The Way to Wealth.”",
          "answer": "Poor Richard’s Almanack"
        },
        {
          "question": "Meeting where Franklin served on the Committee of Five, which drafted the Declaration of Independence.",
          "answer": "Second Continental Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current US state whose last Royal Governor was William Franklin, Ben’s illegitimate son.",
          "answer": "New Jersey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current US state where Jonesborough served as the unrecognized State of Franklin’s capital.",
          "answer": "Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Food that caused Franklin to give up vegetarianism in 1723; the UK and Iceland “fought” a war over these creatures in 1976.",
          "answer": "cod"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Scottish-immigrant vigilante frontiersman that threatened Philadelphia during Pontiac’s Rebellion until Franklin intervened.",
          "answer": "Paxton Boys"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Kingdom of Poland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religious group that often settled in Poland after escaping persecution in the rest of Europe, then were targeted in the Holocaust.",
          "answer": "Jews"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current capital of Poland, since it was moved by Sigismund III.",
          "answer": "Warsaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "Original capital of Poland, where Casimir III founded one of the oldest universities in the world.",
          "answer": "Krak´ow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country to the north that invaded Poland during the Deluge and governed from Stockholm.",
          "answer": "Sweden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crusading order that fought the Kingdom of Poland for control of Prussia.",
          "answer": [
            "Teutonic Knights or the Teutonic Order",
            "the Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that joined with Poland in a personal union and, later, a namesake commonwealth.",
          "answer": "Lithuania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paralyzing policy that allowed any noble to veto legislation in that commonwealth’s Sejm [same] by simply yelling “I do not allow!”",
          "answer": "Liberum veto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that ruled Poland’s Golden Age after the Piasts. Its members included Jadwiga [yad-vee-gah] of Poland.",
          "answer": "Jagiellonian Dynasty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Silver",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Island where the Romans mined silver behind the protection of Hadrian’s Wall.",
          "answer": "Great Britain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island nation that exported silver from its Iwami Ginzan mines to the Dutch.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American country named for silver. A river that borders it to the north, the R´ıo de la Plata, is also named for silver.",
          "answer": "Argentina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lode of silver ore that sparked a silver rush to Nevada’s Virginia Range in 1859.",
          "answer": "Comstock Lode"
        },
        {
          "question": "Silver and gold alloy used to make the first coins in Lydia.",
          "answer": "electrum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that provided the Habsburgs with silver from the town of Kutn´a Hora. It came under a personal union with Austria in 1526.",
          "answer": "Bohemia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region split between Austria and Italy that was home to Habsburg silver mines at St. Johann.",
          "answer": "Tyrol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain of silver exploited by the Spanish after their conquest of modern Bolivia.",
          "answer": "Cerro Potos´ı"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a letter to his cousin Lund, the owner of these objects notes that two of them were “in the secret drawer” of a locker. Jean-Pierre Le Mayeur befriended the owner of these objects in 1781 and helped maintain them. A letter asking for equipment to care for these objects noted there was (20 pts)",
        "“little prospect of being in [Philadelphia] soon;” that letter was intercepted by the British and may have convinced Henry Clinton to not reinforce Yorktown. Contrary to (10 pts)",
        "legend, wood was not used to fashion a replacement set of these objects, which are now on display at Mount Vernon. For ten points, name these body parts that made public speaking difficult for the first US President."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Washington’s false and/or real teeth",
        "clear equivalents",
        "George Washington’s dentures",
        "similar equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In January 2017, protests erupted against this leader over increases in gas prices known as the “Gasolinazo.” The “I am 132” movement was established to protest this leader’s 2012 election. This leader was heavily criticized for inaction over the 2014 (20 pts)",
        "kidnapping of 43 students in Iguala. This man’s namesake “bots” spread propaganda in favor of him and his party, the (10 pts)",
        "PRI. This leader canceled a meeting with Donald Trump after he said his country would refuse to pay for a border wall. For ten points, name this current President of Mexico."
      ],
      "answer": "Enrique Pen˜a Nieto"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Athenians who performed a special type of this process were known as cleruchs; the first such example was probably done at Salamis. A brand from an original prytaneum was used in the (20 pts)",
        "ceremonial beginning of this process, which started taking place in Ionia, Thrace, and Italy in the 700s BC. (10 pts)",
        "Syracuse was created as a result of, for ten points, what general process that spread ancient Greek culture and, more crucially, people, throughout the Mediterranean?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ancient Greek colonization",
        "word forms",
        "descriptions of ancient Greeks settling new cities",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Honeywell, Inc. v. Sperry Rand Corp overturned a patent created during this project, which was originally called “Project PX.” John Brainerd was the lead investigator during this project, which intrigued John von Neumann enough to lead to its use in (20 pts)",
        "H-bomb development at Los Alamos. This project was initially commissioned by the Ballistic Research Laboratory to calculate artillery tables at the University of Pennsylvania, and it became fully operational in 1946. (10 pts)",
        "Kay McNulty was one of six women who programmed, for ten points, what “Great Brain” that is often considered the first electronic computer?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ENIAC",
        "Electronic Numerical Integrator and Computer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man ended a mutiny by declaring to his men “I am waiting for the tanks and the Americans” before launching another attack. After Erich von Falkenhayn declared that he would bleed this man’s troops (20 pts)",
        "white in one battle, this man allegedly rallied his men with the cry “they shall not pass.” The “Sacred Way” supply line was established by this (10 pts)",
        "marshal, who worked with Pierre Laval in a post-military position that earned him life imprisonment. For ten points, name this war hero at Verdun who collaborated with the Nazis as the head of Vichy France."
      ],
      "answer": "Philippe Petain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The leader of the losing side of this war was killed by a man known as “Frank the Devil.” The Campaign of the Hills was the final phase of this conflict, which included the siege of the Fortress of Humait´a. (20 pts)",
        "Rutherford B. Hayes helped lead negotiations in the aftermath of this conflict which included the Battle of Tuyut´ı. Eliza Lynch was the wife of the leader of the losing country, which lost over (10 pts)",
        "two-thirds of its adult male population. Francisco Solano L´opez was killed in, for ten points, what war in which Paraguay was defeated by Argentina, Brazil, and Uruguay?"
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Triple Alliance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before this battle, a character claims that “the ransom of my bold attempt / Shall be this cold corpse on the earth’s cold face” should he die in combat. The night prior to this battle, a man states “It is now (20 pts)",
        "dead midnight. / Cold fearful drops stand on my trembling flesh. / What do I fear? Myself?” after begin visited by a parade of vengeful ghosts who instruct him to despair and die. At this battle, the losing commander exclaims (10 pts)",
        "“A horse! a horse! my kingdom for a horse!” For ten points, name this climactic Shakespearean battle in which Richard III is killed."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Bosworth Field"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Buffalo Bill rode up to this figure and bowed to her at the Chicago World’s Fair. Ann Gordon argues that pro-life depictions of this figure are an example of “invented memory.” This woman worked with (20 pts)",
        "George Train as the publisher of a weekly newspaper called The Revolution; that paper put her ten thousand dollars in debt, according to testimony in which she declared “I shall never (10 pts)",
        "pay a dollar of your unjust penalty” after being arrested in Rochester after attempting to vote. For ten points, name this advocate for women’s suffrage who was honored on a 20th century dollar coin."
      ],
      "answer": "Susan Brownell Anthony"
    }
  ]
}